<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Sriya&#x27;s Website</title>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://sriya-g.github.io/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sriya-g.github.io"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2026-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://sriya-g.github.io/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Cool stuff (ongoing)</title>
        <published>2026-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2026-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/cool-stuff-ongoing/"/>
        <id>https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/cool-stuff-ongoing/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/cool-stuff-ongoing/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;blog-posts&quot;&gt;Blog Posts&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;aboutfeeds.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;About Feeds&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&#x27;ve ever been confused about the orange wifi symbol thing you see on some websites and blogs, read this!&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;stephango.com&#x2F;file-over-app&quot;&gt;File over app&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why I prefer applications that trust me to handle my own files&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;drmollytov.smol.pub&#x2F;2026-02-16&quot;&gt;what does &quot;learn to use a computer&quot; mean, anyway?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&quot;Handing our kids iPads or Chromebooks is not teaching them to be &#x27;computer literate,&#x27; except in the worst end-user, raw-materials-for-data-extraction, corporate-drone sense.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Still buying CDs in 2026</title>
        <published>2026-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2026-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/still-buying-cds-in-2026/"/>
        <id>https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/still-buying-cds-in-2026/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/still-buying-cds-in-2026/">&lt;p&gt;I used to use Spotify. I was on the Free plan, so I could only listen to music on shuffle, and I had a limited number of skips each hour. It basically turned my music listening experience into a slot machine, pulling the lever six times to see if I&#x27;d get one of the songs I wanted from each playlist. At some point, I also noticed that playlist shuffle song sequences would repeat, with some songs always coming after other songs in a predictable way. &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;community.spotify.com&#x2F;t5&#x2F;Desktop-Windows&#x2F;Shuffle-mode-playing-the-same-songs-all-the-time&#x2F;td-p&#x2F;5280042&quot;&gt;Others&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; have had this issue too. Even if it was a deliberate design choice, I disagree with it. If shuffle isn&#x27;t truly random, why label it as shuffle in the first place? I&#x27;m sure I would have had a far better experience if I paid for Spotify Premium, but as a high school student with no income, it wasn&#x27;t possible for me at the time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after I graduated high school, I deleted my Spotify account and decided to start collecting CDs. I wanted to &quot;own&quot; my music, and I personally prefer buying CDs to buying digital albums. I can pick up a CD, read the booklet it (usually) comes with, and use it. It&#x27;s like functional merch for my favorite artists, and even brand new, it&#x27;s usually around the same price or only slightly more expensive than the digital version of the album. If you buy the CD used, it might even be cheaper. I&#x27;ve bought CDs for literally 25 cents that I ended up enjoying. I recommend checking library sales, garage sales, thrift stores, and record stores.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually listen to albums that my friends recommended on services like YouTube (Music) and Bandcamp, track my listens with Last.fm, and then buy the CDs of the albums I listened to the most so I could back them up and listen to them in full quality, offline, with no ads. For me, buying a CD motivates me to give the whole album a try, not just the best-known tracks. I sometimes discovered that I liked almost every song on albums I only listened to two or three tracks of on Spotify. Other times, I realized that an album that didn&#x27;t have many songs I liked when listening to individual songs actually sounded great when it was listened to all together.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, buying CDs means I spend money anyway. As of right now, base Spotify Premium is $13 per month (I could get a student discount, but if I paid for Premium, I would probably end up doing it long term). The CDs I buy new are usually around $10-12 each, so instead of listening to any of the millions of songs available on Spotify&#x27;s catalogs, I get to add about 10 new songs to my &quot;catalog&quot; per month. This seems like a bad deal, but I tend to listen to the same albums over and over again, so it&#x27;s not like I would take advantage of the whole Spotify catalog anyway. Also, if the price increased so much I was no longer willing to pay it, features I care about were moved to higher paid tiers, or I just decided to stop using Spotify, I would have nothing to show for the money I&#x27;d spent over the years.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-music-discovery&quot;&gt;What about music discovery?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s true that I discovered some of my current favorite artists through Spotify recommendations and playlists. But more often than not, I would only listen to the few songs that got recommended to me, not the rest of the artist&#x27;s discography. Since my free plan had limited skips and played plenty of ads, I usually just tried to listen to my favorite songs before I ran out of skips or the ads got too annoying. I didn&#x27;t want to waste skips or waste time listening to ads just to hear a song that I ended up not liking.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought my first CD (&quot;I Do Not Want What I Haven&#x27;t Got&quot; by Sinéad O&#x27;Connor) at a used item sale right before my first semester began. I recognized the artist&#x27;s name, and the CD only cost a dollar, so I decided to take a chance on the album and bought it. I didn&#x27;t have a CD player at my dorm yet, so I looked up the album online. I ended up listening to &quot;Nothing Compares 2 U&quot; on repeat. This song, and album, probably never would have been recommended to me by Spotify&#x27;s algorithm because I mostly listen to upbeat pop and electronic music.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spotify is not the only way to discover music. Many of my all-time favorite albums were recommended to me by my friends. There&#x27;s no shortage of music critics and articles online who usually have their own recommendations. Sometimes I find interesting new albums by browsing Bandcamp&#x27;s top sold albums in my favorite genres. Even if you would prefer a personalized music algorithm based on your own listening tastes, Last.fm has worked ok for me and lets me aggregate my listening from many different platforms (There are also self hosted options.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;buying-cds-vs-digital-albums&quot;&gt;Buying CDs vs. digital albums&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If 99% of the time I listen to my CD backup (through my self hosted streaming or iPod) and not directly from the CD itself, why do I bother buying the CD, which takes up valuable shelf space and can&#x27;t be delivered instantaneously?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Services like Bandcamp, Qobuz, and occasionally some artist websites let you buy music files. (I don&#x27;t count services where you &quot;buy&quot; music that is then locked to their proprietary platform as &quot;buying&quot; music unless you can get the actual files with no DRM. I don&#x27;t want to rely on a service that could get shut down some day and then lose all of my purchased music.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I chose to buy music files instead of CDs, I could skip the part where I go to a store in person&#x2F;wait for my CD to get delivered and back up the CD, and skip straight to adding the album to my streaming and iPod. This has some benefits: not needing the cardboard and plastic of the CD and its packaging, saving shelf space, avoiding shipping costs and environmental effects, and less effort on my part.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many (not all) cases, the digital album music files cost as much as a brand new CD would, or even slightly more. This may be worth it to you if the files are 24-bit FLACs compared to only 16-bit CD quality, but personally I can&#x27;t usually tell the difference, and CD quality is good enough for me. More importantly, if I&#x27;m already paying $10+, I prefer to have something physical for that money, something I can hold. I only consider buying digital files if the CD has limited availability (especially when combined with high shipping costs from the few available sources) or the digital files are significantly cheaper than the CD.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Calendar and Tasks Clients on Linux</title>
        <published>2026-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2026-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/calendar-and-tasks-clients-on-linux/"/>
        <id>https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/calendar-and-tasks-clients-on-linux/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/calendar-and-tasks-clients-on-linux/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been looking for good to-do &amp;amp; calendar app(s) for over a year now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I started self hosting my calendar and to-dos, I used Google Calendar and Tasks. These worked perfectly for my use case. I created a different list for each of my classes, and tasks with due dates showed up on my calendar.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, I decided I wanted to start moving away from exclusively using Google services, and I started using Proton Calendar. Proton didn&#x27;t have anything like Tasks at the time (although it seems to be &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;protonmail.uservoice.com&#x2F;forums&#x2F;284483-proton-mail-calendar&#x2F;suggestions&#x2F;7158378-proton-tasks-to-do-list&quot;&gt;highly requested&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;proton.me&#x2F;blog&#x2F;proton-mail-calendar-roadmap&quot;&gt;potentially in progress&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, as of me writing this, they still don&#x27;t) so I started writing my to-do list on paper, thinking this was a perfect time to start being more analog.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It didn&#x27;t work out very well. I&#x27;m used to features like recurring tasks and sync over multiple devices, which a paper notebook doesn&#x27;t have. I would forget to write tasks down and forget to bring my notebook with me. By the end of last semester, I knew I needed to go back to digital tasks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On iOS, the Calendar and Reminders apps sync perfectly with CalDAV and have all of the features I want (although subtasks apparently &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;help.nextcloud.com&#x2F;t&#x2F;sub-tasks-in-apple-reminders&#x2F;167668&quot;&gt;don&#x27;t work properly&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I don&#x27;t use them.) The UI looks great too, and the apps are intuitive to use.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&#x27;m being productive, getting tasks done, I tend to be on my laptop. I also tend to put my phone away so I don&#x27;t get distracted, so I need access to my tasks and calendar on my laptop too. For a while, I used the Nextcloud web client to manage my tasks and calendar, which works fine and has all of the features I need. However, I personally dislike having extra browser tabs open, and the website can take a while to load, so I decided to look for Calendar and Tasks clients.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-i-wanted&quot;&gt;What I Wanted&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Loads reasonably fast&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Looks nice&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both calendars and tasks in one application&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Optional but highly preferred) &quot;All tasks&quot; view (or equivalent) groups tasks by which list they&#x27;re in, and labels this information prominently. Extra points for also color coding tasks based on list.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Probably impossible to find) A calendar&#x2F;tasks widget to put on my desktop so I can view upcoming events easily&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-search-begins&quot;&gt;The Search Begins!&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;korganizer-kontact&quot;&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apps.kde.org&#x2F;korganizer&#x2F;&quot;&gt;KOrganizer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&#x2F;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apps.kde.org&#x2F;kontact&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Kontact&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use KDE Plasma, so this was already installed on my laptop. KOrganizer has calendar and to-do lists, while Kontact (which incorporates KOrganizer) adds mail, contacts, and RSS feeds, basically making it a personal start page. Since I don&#x27;t need the extra features of Kontact, I&#x27;ll focus on KOrganizer, though I will mention that somehow the colors I set for different calendars on Nextcloud worked automatically on KOrganizer but not Kontact.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was able to add my calendar account pretty easily, and both my calendars and tasks lists synced over. It doesn&#x27;t have the tasks view I wanted, and it doesn&#x27;t look as modern as some of the other options on this list, but it works and satisfies most of my requirements.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;merkuro&quot;&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apps.kde.org&#x2F;merkuro&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Merkuro&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merkuro (formerly Kalendar?) is also by KDE. It has similar functions to KOrganizer, but with a refreshed UI.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reeeeally wanted this to work! I installed it, my calendar and tasks were already synced (probably because I set up my Nextcloud account with KOrganizer) and I immediately loved how the UI looked. Tasks still weren&#x27;t grouped the way I wanted (at least by default; it&#x27;s possible there was a setting somewhere I didn&#x27;t see) but they were at least color coded by list.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, when I tried to make a task, the application crashed. I tried reopening and making another task, and the same thing happened. I uninstalled and reinstalled, same issue still. Over the half dozen times I tried to make a task while troubleshooting, I only got to the task creation screen once, and I was so surprised I exited out by accident. I never made it back.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I probably could have gone further in finding the exact error that occurred and searching for a fix online, but I decided to move on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;gnome-calendar&quot;&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apps.gnome.org&#x2F;Calendar&#x2F;&quot;&gt;GNOME Calendar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, this one is only a calendar, no to-do lists. I initially installed it via the Fedora repo, and while the app looked really nice, I couldn&#x27;t figure out how to add my Nextcloud account. Clicking on any of the settings options did nothing. I gave up and uninstalled it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I later went back and tried the Flatpak version. I&#x27;m not sure what I did between my first try and my second one, but my calendar was actually synced already. The settings options still did nothing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, not having the due dates of my to-do items on my calendar is a deal breaker. The UI of this calendar is really nice though.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;thunderbird&quot;&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.thunderbird.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Thunderbird&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thunderbird is best known as an email client, but it also has calendar and task features. Since I didn&#x27;t want to use Thunderbird for emails, I found the setup to be slightly confusing. I eventually found out how to add my Nextcloud account for calendars and tasks only, and everything synced over well.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only used this briefly, so I don&#x27;t remember my exact experiences well. I didn&#x27;t like the tasks UI and didn&#x27;t need the email client aspect, so I moved on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;evolution&quot;&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gitlab.gnome.org&#x2F;GNOME&#x2F;evolution&quot;&gt;Evolution&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to Thunderbird, this is also an email client with calendars and tasks. I backed out of the email setup, then started adding my calendars and tasks lists. I say &quot;started&quot; because I seemingly had to add them one at a time. It&#x27;s possible that there was an option to add every calendar and list at once, but it wasn&#x27;t obvious to me anywhere on the UI or during the calendar adding process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each time I wanted to add a new calendar or task list, I would have to paste my Nextcloud URL, type in my long username and password, and then manually select a single calendar or list. This wasn&#x27;t so bad for my calendars, because I only have two, but I have a task list for every class I&#x27;m taking and a few extras.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Halfway through adding my lists, I decided to give up so I could finish tasks on them instead. (Or procrastinate by writing this)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;cfait&quot;&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;codeberg.org&#x2F;trougnouf&#x2F;cfait&quot;&gt;cfait&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is interesting because it offers both a TUI and a GUI. It&#x27;s also only for tasks, so I would need a separate app for viewing my calendar.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I installed it through cargo and tried both the TUI and GUI. After logging in to my Nextcloud, I spent some time on the TUI trying to get used to the keybinds. While I&#x27;m fine with using the terminal for some tasks, and even prefer it in some cases, I&#x27;m just too used to clicking on to-do boxes. Given a little more time, I probably could have adapted to the TUI, but I really wanted to try the GUI.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GUI was almost perfect. The task view color codes tasks based on which list they&#x27;re from, and the UI looks great with many color scheme options. There was no way to maximize the window, though. Even when I increased the size of the window to fill my monitor screen, it went back to the default size the next time the application was reopened.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really want my calendar and tasks to be accessible from the same application, but if I changed my mind, I might come back to this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-winner-is&quot;&gt;The Winner Is...&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... none of the above?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I went back to using Nextcloud Web&#x27;s Calendar and Tasks pages. UI and reliability matter the most to me, and although KOrganizer came close, the way it showed task lists made it difficult for me to tell which task belonged to which list at a glance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might look back into Merkuro in the future. Hopefully it works by then, or I at least have more time to troubleshoot.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m also sort of tempted to write my own client, though I haven&#x27;t looked into how CalDAV works at all. Maybe next break!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone has any other recommendations, please reach out to me on Matrix!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>The Homelab Experience</title>
        <published>2026-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2026-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/the-homelab-experience/"/>
        <id>https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/the-homelab-experience/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/the-homelab-experience/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a while now, I&#x27;ve been trying to get my data away from various cloud storage providers. I&#x27;ve been storing most of my files locally, but with only 300 GB allocated to my main Fedora install on my laptop, this isn&#x27;t plausible in the long term.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have an old PC lying around at home, and I&#x27;ve briefly entertained the idea of self hosting before. I usually dismiss it for various reasons. I don&#x27;t currently have a domain name, I haven&#x27;t looked much into software options, etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About two weeks ago, I had some free time and decided to just start setting up &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tailscale.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Tailscale&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;nextcloud.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Nextcloud&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;setup&quot;&gt;Setup&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was way easier than I expected.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, the hardest part might have been setting up my PC. It used to be home to a Windows 11&#x2F;Ubuntu dual boot, until I broke GRUB trying to install Linux Mint too -- the only survivor was the Windows install. The CPU didn&#x27;t have official support for Windows 11 (it&#x27;s a still-capable i7 that&#x27;s just one generation too old) but I installed it through Windows Insider Preview a few years ago. Unfortunately, it refused to update properly, and I realized running W11 might not be feasible. It was time to switch back to Linux.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose Ubuntu again for software compatibility. It also seems to be a popular choice for running servers, so I rationalized i&#x27;d be able to find other people with my problem if a problem did arise.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only factor holding me back was that I didn&#x27;t have a spare USB drive to use as installation media. I was very close to using an old Note 8 when I found a generic 8gb drive. To make future installs and livebooting easier for myself, I set up Ventoy on the drive.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bizarrely, I was unable to access the BIOS with the HDMI plugged into my GPU, which was annoying. My &quot;fix&quot; was to just install Ubuntu with the HDMI plugged into the motherboard, then set up the GPU after the install finished.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;actual-setup&quot;&gt;Actual setup&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set up Tailscale on my laptop, PC, and iPhone. Then, I followed &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;nextcloud&#x2F;all-in-one&#x2F;discussions&#x2F;6817&quot;&gt;this guide&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to set up my Nextcloud on the PC.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s it! I was able to access my Nextcloud on my laptop and phone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;sidenote-syncthing&quot;&gt;Sidenote: Syncthing&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, Syncthing was my main method of sharing files between devices. KOReader has a &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;jasonchoimtt&#x2F;koreader-syncthing&quot;&gt;Syncthing plugin&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, so I started using it for eBooks because my Kindle e-reader doesn&#x27;t support USB file transfer while in KOReader. Later, I added my iPhone (with &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;pixelspark&#x2F;sushitrain&quot;&gt;Synctrain&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) so that I could read the same books on my Kindle and phone. For the most part, this worked. Occasionally I ran into issues with annotation metadata file conflicts if I read the same book on KOReader on both my Kindle and laptop, but I usually read different books on different devices so it didn&#x27;t happen often.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I switched to Obsidian on iPhone, I wanted to sync my notes too, which is when I discovered a major limitation. I wasn&#x27;t able to pick my vault location on iOS -- I had to have the vault inside the &quot;Obsidian&quot; folder on my iPhone. This meant that I wouldn&#x27;t be able to directly use my vault folder in Nextcloud as the source for my notes. I was able to set Synctrain to sync my Obsidian vaults to this folder.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I set up Nextcloud, I backed up my eBooks and notes, but realized that I needed to maintain Syncthing for my Kindle ebooks. &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tailscale.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;tailscale-jailbroken-kindle&quot;&gt;It is possible&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;blog.papermatch.me&#x2F;html&#x2F;Tailscale_on_Kindle&quot;&gt;set up Tailscale on a modded Kindle&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but it felt like overkill. I also needed some way of making sure my Obsidian vaults were mirrored directly to the Obsidian folder on my phone, and since Syncthing was working, I decided to keep it. I changed the Syncthing directory on my laptop for both folders to be in the directory I sync to Nextcloud.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does mean my setup is more complex, since my note edits on iPhone don&#x27;t automatically save to the cloud. I just need to remember to sync them (and my eBooks on my Kindle) with my laptop every once in a while.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-favorite-features&quot;&gt;My Favorite Features&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I finished setting up the Nextcloud instance, I had a moment of looking at the tabs for all of the different apps and being overwhelmed at just how much was included.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next few days, I explored the features and found my favorites.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;calendar-and-tasks&quot;&gt;Calendar and Tasks&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been looking for a good alternative to Google Calendar&#x2F;Tasks for a while now. I used Proton Calendar for a year, but it doesn&#x27;t have a Tasks equivalent right now. My replacement was a running list of To Dos on paper, which lacked several features I care about (sync, putting task due dates on the calendar.) Other options I explored online lacked these features, or they were proprietary, or had too many features I didn&#x27;t want that would get in my way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, Nextcloud Calendar and Tasks are great replacements that do exactly what I want, and they sync with the native iOS Calendar and Reminders apps with CalDAV.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;music&quot;&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;nc-music&#x2F;music&quot;&gt;Music&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted an app to listen to my music collection, so I decided to try this. I liked the way the UI looked, and the Last.fm scrobbling support and Subsonic compatibility were promising. One of the main frustrations of trying to listen to music locally on my iPhone was that no app I checked had client-side scrobbling support for local music. Last.fm is the main way I aggregate my listening data from all the different places I listen to music (&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.strawberrymusicplayer.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Strawberry&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, my iPod, Bandcamp, YouTube.) VLC on iOS is amazing, it has a great UI and supports many different file types, but I eventually gave up on listening to local music files on my iPhone because I had no way to log it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*sidenote: the awesome &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;web-scrobbler&#x2F;web-scrobbler&quot;&gt;Web Scrobbler&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has a &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apps.apple.com&#x2F;us&#x2F;app&#x2F;web-scrobbler&#x2F;id6449224218&quot;&gt;Safari extension&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that works on iOS. I only found out about this a few weeks ago, but I used it until I set up my homelab. If you find yourself mostly using the browser versions of the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;webscrobbler.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;many, many websites&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; supported by Web Scrobbler, give it a try!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set up the Last.fm integration by adding my API key, downloaded an amazing Subsonic client on my iPhone (&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;BLeeEZ&#x2F;amperfy&quot;&gt;Amperfy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), configured Subsonic on Strawberry and Amperfy, and started streaming my music.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It worked perfectly! I was even able to scrobble the tracks I listened to on my iPhone. Amperfy also supports lyrics, which finally motivated me to use &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;tranxuanthang&#x2F;lrcget&quot;&gt;LRCGET&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to get the .lrc (lyric) files for most of my library.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably my favorite part of the entire homelab setup. I can&#x27;t thank the people behind the Music app and Amperfy enough.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Software that brought me joy in 2025</title>
        <published>2026-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2026-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/software-that-brought-me-joy-in-2025/"/>
        <id>https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/software-that-brought-me-joy-in-2025/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/software-that-brought-me-joy-in-2025/">&lt;p&gt;This isn&#x27;t a definitive list at all. I just wanted to highlight some of my favorite software that I began using in 2025.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fedora&quot;&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fedoraproject.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Fedora&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2025 was the year I finally worked up the courage to switch to a Linux distribution on my main laptop.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used Windows for most of my life, but a combination of disliking the design changes between Windows 10 and 11 and an interest in Linux&#x27;s user customization finally pushed me to try it out. A few years ago, I tried Linux Mint and Manjaro in VMs, ended up liking KDE Plasma more than Cinnamon, and dual booted Manjaro on an old laptop. I didn&#x27;t use the install much, because the laptop had  a dead battery and was forever tethered to a wall, but it gave me my first taste of what running Linux on real hardware was like. When I got my new (current) laptop, I was initially too scared to install Linux and potentially &quot;mess it up,&quot; so I stuck to Windows 11.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started college, I joined the UIUC GNU&#x2F;Linux User Group (GLUG) and met a lot of people who used Linux daily. Seeing that they were able to do college coursework with almost no issues on Linux gave me confidence to try it myself. In fact, I chose Fedora because I already knew other students who daily drove it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January of last year, I dual booted Fedora and... basically didn&#x27;t use it for six months. I really enjoyed how customizable everything was (With a combination of various themes I found online, I made my install look almost exactly like Windows 7) but my entire life was still on the laptop&#x27;s Windows install.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in June, I decided it was time to migrate all of my data to the Fedora install, which is probably one of the best decisions I&#x27;ve ever made. Except for the rare cases where software isn&#x27;t compatible with Linux, I never boot into Windows.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re curious about my Fedora install, check out my &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;sriya-g&#x2F;dotfiles&quot;&gt;dotfiles&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;rockbox&quot;&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.rockbox.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Rockbox&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2025 was also the year I attempted my first hardware repair, replacing the battery and storage in an old iPod Photo. After replacing the broken hard drive with a CF to SD card converter and a CF to IDE board, I decided to run Rockbox for its features and themes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to run modern software on my iPod from 2005 is amazing. It took less than 5 minutes to install and includes every feature I&#x27;d want in digital audio player software. It can play my FLACs and I can store my listening history to upload to my last.fm account. I use the &lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;themes.rockbox.org&#x2F;index.php?themeid=3151&amp;amp;target=ipodcolor&quot;&gt;Interpod&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; theme, which is really modern and clean looking, almost like if Apple Music ran on iPods.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience isn&#x27;t perfect -- I occasionally have an issue where the iPod throws an out of memory error halfway into the first song it plays after turning on, and I have to requeue songs (though everything plays perfectly afterward for the rest of the session). The cause could be some combination of having nearly 60 gigabytes of music, trying to play large FLAC files and queue up long playlists on a device with only 32 MB of ram, and hardware damage from sitting unused and nonfunctional in a drawer for over 10 years. It hasn&#x27;t been annoying enough for me to try to fix yet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering I can play lossless audio on a 20 year old portable music player and share my listening history from it online with my friends, I&#x27;m more than happy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;iamb&quot;&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;external&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;iamb.chat&#x2F;&quot;&gt;iamb&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast, reliable, and I didn&#x27;t have the same issues with trying to get my session verified that I did with Neochat. I ended up building an rpm from source (my first time ever doing this) and switched to Kitty to get image support. When I want to use Matrix on my laptop, iamb is my go-to client.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existence of iamb makes me appreciate open source protocols more. The official Discord client is fine, but I enjoy having options.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;and-beyond&quot;&gt;...and beyond?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started off 2026 by turning an old PC into a homelab, and considering how much joy it&#x27;s brought me so far, it&#x27;ll definitely make this year&#x27;s list. Blogpost soon.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Microjournaling is awesome :D</title>
        <published>2025-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/microjournaling/"/>
        <id>https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/microjournaling/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://sriya-g.github.io/blog/microjournaling/">&lt;p&gt;Last year, my sister gifted me a tiny 2025 dated planner. I probably should have used it as a planner (my current &quot;planner&quot; is a regular notebook, where I keep a running checklist of undated To Dos) but I decided to use it as a microjournal instead.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back when I was in middle and high school, I wrote literal pages every single day. When I was bored, I would just start writing down all of my thoughts. I still have those journals (though I&#x27;m not brave enough to take another look at them!) When I started college, I assumed I would have much less free time and left journaling behind. Literally. I left my journal at home, hundreds of miles away.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was true that I had less free time at college, but I spent most of my first semester wishing I had my journal so I could reflect on all of the novel experiences I was having. Somewhere around New Years Eve, I decided to use my new planner as a low-commitment daily journal. Each space is only ~2 square inches, so there&#x27;s barely enough room for a few sentences. It would take me less than a minute to fill a day&#x27;s space with a few sentences.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&#x27;t really my New Years resolution, but I mostly kept up with writing every day! There were a few days (especially during the summer) where I would forget to write, but I filled in those days during the week. Once I started my second year of college, I kept my microjournal on my desk. It acted as a visual reminder to write about my day, which I usually did before I went to sleep.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflecting in my microjournal also led me to discover new things about myself. I noticed all of the entries where I complained about wasting my time doomscrolling when I had work to do usually also mentioned that I was exhausted. I started a new practice: if I felt tired and noticed myself going off task, I would just go to sleep, even if it was still relatively &quot;early&quot; compared to when I usually slept. Then I would wake up early and get the work done. This made my work more manageable and made me feel a bit better about myself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem I ran into was that on days where I did a lot, I usually ran out of space when trying to describe everything. During one vacation, I accidentally left the journal at home. I kept up my journalling on the Notes app on my phone, but when I got back, I had some trouble fitting my recollections in the space corresponding to each day. I also noticed that the entries on my phone slowly got longer throughout the vacation - not necessarily because I was doing more, but because without the space restraint of my microjournal, I tended to go into more detail about my day.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I think the space restraint of my tiny journal was necessary. Back when I was writing pages every day in my larger journals, I made myself finish each page I was on. That meant that if I was halfway through a page and ran out of thoughts, I just started rambling until the end of the page. Sometimes, my rambling sparked something interesting and I started writing more. Other times, it was just rambling. Either way, I set a standard for myself of writing at least one full page for each entry. Considering I have less free time now, forcing myself to write one full page every day would probably just end in me abandoning my journal within a week. With my microjournal, I get the satisfaction of filling the space for each day without feeling like writing is a huge commitment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back at my entries for this year is going to be fun. I can&#x27;t justify buying a 2026 dated planner when I have a stack of unused notebooks, but I&#x27;ll continue microjournalling next year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
